<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-18T04:03:12-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Joshua Payapulli</title><subtitle>Portfolio</subtitle><author><name>Joshua Payapulli</name></author><entry><title type="html">Linear Regression, KNN Regression: Combined Cycle Power Plant Data</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data%20science/ccpp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Linear Regression, KNN Regression: Combined Cycle Power Plant Data" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data%20science/ccpp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data%20science/ccpp/"><![CDATA[<p>This project delves into a detailed dataset from a Combined Cycle Power Plant over six years (2006-2011), where the main goal is to predict the net hourly electrical energy output (EP). The dataset features include hourly average ambient variables: Temperature (T), Ambient Pressure (AP), Relative Humidity (RH), and Exhaust Vacuum (V)…</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="project-overview">Project Overview</h2>
<p>The project begins with downloading and exploring the dataset, examining the number of rows and columns, and understanding what they represent. This step includes making scatterplots of all variables and observing the relationships between independent and dependent variables.</p>

<h2 id="data-analysis-and-insights">Data Analysis and Insights</h2>
<p>Statistical analysis is conducted to find the mean, median, range, quartiles, and interquartile ranges of each variable. This is summarized in a comprehensive table for an easy overview of the data characteristics.</p>

<h2 id="regression-models">Regression Models</h2>
<p>The core of the project involves:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Developing simple linear regression models for each predictor and assessing their significance in predicting the plant’s output.</li>
  <li>Constructing a multiple regression model using all predictors and identifying the most impactful ones.</li>
  <li>A comparative study between univariate and multiple regression models is presented visually.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="advanced-analysis">Advanced Analysis</h2>
<p>The exploration extends to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Examining nonlinear associations between predictors and response using polynomial regression models.</li>
  <li>Investigating interactions between different predictors and their impact on the response.</li>
  <li>A thorough analysis of these models is presented, including the training and testing Mean Squared Errors (MSEs).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="knn-regression">KNN Regression</h2>
<p>The project also includes KNN regression analysis, comparing both normalized and raw features to determine the best fit. The analysis of train and test errors provides valuable insights into the model’s performance.</p>

<h2 id="comparative-study-and-conclusions">Comparative Study and Conclusions</h2>
<p>The project concludes with a comparison between KNN Regression and the most effective linear regression model. This comparative analysis provides a deep understanding of different modeling approaches in predicting energy output in power plants.</p>

<p><a href="https://nbviewer.org/github/Payapulli/Payapulli.github.io/blob/main/jupyter-notebooks/Vertebral-Column-Datset-KNN.ipynb">View Jupyter Notebook</a> | 
<a href="URL_to_your_GitHub_repository">View Project on GitHub</a> |
<a href="https://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/Combined+Cycle+Power+Plant">View Dataset</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Joshua Payapulli</name></author><category term="Data Science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This project delves into a detailed dataset from a Combined Cycle Power Plant over six years (2006-2011), where the main goal is to predict the net hourly electrical energy output (EP). The dataset features include hourly average ambient variables: Temperature (T), Ambient Pressure (AP), Relative Humidity (RH), and Exhaust Vacuum (V)…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">KNN: Vertebral Column Data Set Analysis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data%20science/vertebral/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="KNN: Vertebral Column Data Set Analysis" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data%20science/vertebral</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data%20science/vertebral/"><![CDATA[<p>This project involves a comprehensive analysis of the Vertebral Column Data Set created by Dr. Henrique da Mota. The data set includes six biomechanical attributes from each patient, focusing on binary classification of Normal (NO) and Abnormal (AB) conditions…</p>

<!--more-->

<h2 id="dataset-overview">Dataset Overview</h2>
<p>The dataset is explored through scatterplots and boxplots to understand the relationships and distributions of the variables. A subset of the data is selected as the training and test sets, adhering to specified criteria.</p>

<h2 id="knn-classification">KNN Classification</h2>
<p>The project’s core is implementing K-Nearest Neighbors (KNN) with various metrics including Euclidean, Manhattan, and Chebyshev distances. Key points include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Optimizing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">k</code> value based on error rates.</li>
  <li>Calculating metrics like confusion matrix, true positive and negative rates, precision, and F1-score.</li>
  <li>Analyzing learning curves against different training set sizes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="advanced-techniques">Advanced Techniques</h2>
<p>Further exploration includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Testing different distance metrics and summarizing their performance.</li>
  <li>Implementing weighted voting for improved decision making.</li>
  <li>Evaluating nonlinear associations and interaction terms in regression models.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusions-and-findings">Conclusions and Findings</h2>
<p>The project concludes with insights into the best performing models, optimal <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">k</code> values, and the lowest training error rate achieved.</p>

<p><a href="https://nbviewer.org/github/Payapulli/Payapulli.github.io/blob/main/jupyter-notebooks/Vertebral-Column-Datset-KNN.ipynb">View Jupyter Notebook</a> | 
<a href="URL_to_your_GitHub_repository">View Project on GitHub</a> |
<a href="https://archive.ics.uci.edu/dataset/212/vertebral+column">View Dataset</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Joshua Payapulli</name></author><category term="Data Science" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This project involves a comprehensive analysis of the Vertebral Column Data Set created by Dr. Henrique da Mota. The data set includes six biomechanical attributes from each patient, focusing on binary classification of Normal (NO) and Abnormal (AB) conditions…]]></summary></entry></feed>